Okay, let's go. Today's דף daf *Daf* is י''ב *Yud Bet*, שבועות
Shavuot. י''ב *Shevuos Yud Bet*, and we pick up at the very
bottom of י''א עמוד ב' yud aleph amud bais. *Yud Aleph Amud
Bet*. And we went, we had a fascinating whole statement about רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* about תמידים temidim. *Tmidim*, about communal sacrifices
that what was communal funds, new year comes about, and you have
to use stuff from new funds, and you can redeem these communal
sacrifices even though they don't have a blemish, even though that mechanism
usually is not, that's not work. But here's the way it works,
because of לב בית דין מתנה עליהם Lev Beit Din matneh aleihem.
*Lev Beis Din masneh aleihem*, that there's an implicit stipulation, because, you
know, in this certainly in this case where they know it's going
to happen, but also presumably in other cases as well, possibly an
implicit stipulation that if they need to, you know, that if it
turns out that they don't need this for קרבן korban *Korban*, then
they only wanted to buy it
for an asset and for קדושת סתם *Kedushas stam* and not for
a קרבן korban *Korban*. Okay. And then on the basis of that,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* circled back to ask him about our משנה
Mishnah. *Mishna*, because in our משנה mishnah. *Mishna* they challenged רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*, if you'll remember. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi
Shimon* said רגל regel *Regel*, יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, וראש
חודש *ve'Rosh Chodesh*, the מוסף Musaf *Musaf* of each of them does
a slightly different variation of טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash. וקדשיו *Tumas Mikdash
V'kodashav*, and they said,
if you got, you know, one got leftover, got lost, was rediscovered,
can you use one of those goats for different טומאה *Tumah*? And
he said yes. So they said, why? If there's different, all different
variation, if they're all different types of כפרה kapara. *Kapparah*? And he
said, well, they're variations on a theme and therefore since it's all
about טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash. וקדשיו *Tumas Mikdash V'kodashav* you can do
it. Fine. So the question was, why doesn't רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon,
*Rabbi Shimon*
just
say, hey, after a קרבן korban, *Korban* is lost and rediscovered or
whatever, you can just redeem it even without a blemish if what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* said is correct, that you have
an implicit stipulation? So if there's an implicit stipulation, that just allowed
you to redeem it. So it seems that since he didn't say
that, he doesn't hold of this position. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* conceded the point. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon? *Rabbi Shimon* does
not hold of this position that I just said. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* holds that בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din* does
not stipulate. And therefore it's only because he holds that all these
קרבנות korbanot *Korbanos* are roughly of the same genre that you can
use one for the other, but otherwise you're stuck because בית דין
Beit Din *Beis Din* doesn't stipulate. Okay, so then the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says, so let's pick up from there. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
קאמרת *Rabbi Shimon kamarta*? It is, we'll pick up from like seven
lines from the bottom of י''א עמוד ב' yud aleph amud bais.
*Yud Aleph Amud Bet*. What, you're asking me about רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, לית ליה לב בית דין
מתנה עליהם Lev Beit Din matneh aleihem, *Rabbi Shimon layt lay Lev
Beis Din masneh aleihem*. He doesn't hold that בית דין beis din
*Beis Din* implicitly stipulate. Okay, and therefore you are, you don't have
the ability to redeem it without a blemish if it got lost
and then found again. דאמר רבי אידי בר אבין אמר רב אבין
אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's *De'amar Rabbi Idi bar Avin amar Rav
Avin amar Rabbi Yochanan*, תמידים temidim, שלא הוצרכו לציבור *Tmidim shelo hutzrechu
litzibbur*, if you have this thing I said, that if you had
a תמיד tamid *Tamid* that at the end of the year you,
you know, you didn't use it from the last year's funds, and
I said you could redeem it without a blemish, so I need
to clarify that point. לדידי רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אין נפדים תמימים
temimim *L'didi Rabbi Shimon ein nifdim tmimim*. For רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon*, you can't redeem it without a blemish. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* doesn't hold of my whole חדוש *Chidush* I've been
saying. לדידי חכמים נפדים תמימים temimim *L'didi Chachamim nifdim tmimim*. For the
חכמים *Chachamim*, I was talking according to the חכמים *Chachamim*, you can
redeem it without a blemish. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* I
concede would not say that. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי שמעון מנו *Rabbanan de'pligi alei de'Rabbi Shimon manu*?
So now, who is the rabbis who disagree? Now that you've conceded
that there's a תנא Tanna *Tanna* that doesn't agree with you, who
is the תנא Tanna *Tanna* רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* that
says your position, that you can redeem things without a blemish, okay,
if they're communal? So now what we're basically going to do is
we're going to recap the Tannaitic support that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* brought for his position yesterday. But interestingly, we didn't do
this yesterday, we're going to point out that all of that Tannaitic
support that shows this idea that בית דין beis din *Beis Din*
implicitly stipulate would not necessarily extend it to the idea of the
תמיד tamid. *Tamid*. Okay, so let's take a look why, and we're
going to make distinctions we didn't make yesterday. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, who are those rabbis? Who's that תנא Tanna *Tanna* that
now agrees with your position? מנו *Manu*? אילימא רבנן דקטורת *Eilima Rabbanan
de'Ketores*, which is where we started from, that when you have leftover
incense from the previous year, you can redeem it on money and
then, you know, buy, rebuy it with new monies. Okay, so if
that's true, right, that's like a תמיד tamid. *Tamid* because it's unblemished
and you're redeeming it. So no, that doesn't necessarily lead to your
position. שאני קטורת דלאו בר רעייה היא *Shani Ketores de'lav bar re'iyah
hi*. קטורת *Ketores* you have nothing to, you have no choices with
it. Okay, by the קטורת *Ketores* if you can't redeem it, what
are you going to do with it? There's nothing, you're stuck. But
an animal, if we say you can't redeem it without a blemish,
you've got a choice. You know what your choice is? Let it
graze until it gets a blemish. So just because you say we
do that by קטורת *Ketores*, so maybe we agree to the principle,
there is this idea of לב בית דין מתנה lev beis din
masna, עליהם *Lev Beis Din masneh aleihem*, but it's not so clear
that we would agree with your scope. Just because you do it
by קטורת *Ketores* doesn't mean you would do it by other things.
אלא Ella, רבנן דפרה *Ela Rabbanan de'Parah*. How about the rabbis by
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah *Parah Adumah* where we said there too,
when they needed to, they would be able to redeem it and
buy something else with it, and there was a
whole question of
was that... Of course there too, most of those cases you don't
have a choice. You can't wait for it to get a blemish.
The animal, the animal died. Okay, so what are you supposed to
do? Okay, but there was one choice, you found a nicer one.
So if you just found a nicer one, let the first one
wait till it gets a blemish, so that seems to prove your
point. So the גמרא Gemara says: "No, דילמא שאני פרה דדמיה יקרין."
dilma shani Parah dedamei yakrin. Maybe פרה Parah is different, it's expensive.
We sort of discussed the other day why does expensive, how does
that help you in this case, because the money you already spent
on the first one is a loss, but anyway, so I still
don't really know the answer. But the basic point is, is that
you can't learn out from פרה אדומה Parah Adumah to other things.
Okay? Maybe by פרה אדומה Parah Adumah we were willing to do
it because it's a special circumstance, פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. is a
big deal, we want to be more, you know, maybe we want
to get the absolute best one and so we want more flexibility.
But it doesn't prove we would do it by something where you
have another option like the תמידים. tmidim, You could wait for it
to get a blemish and it's not such a big deal, so
it doesn't prove that we would say it. ואלא רבנן דאמרו לו.
Ve'ella Rabanan de'amru lo. It's the Rabbis of "amru lo," meaning the
Rabbis who challenged רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon When the Rabbis challenged רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and they said, "What would happen if you would
lose one, could you use it for another?" And the implication would
be that they would be saying, "Look רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon for
us it's good. We get that if you lost for one מוסף
Mussaf you can use for the other. But how does it work
for you?" So why is it good for you? I mean, what
was the,
what was the position of the interlocutor? Was that a good word,
use of that word? Okay, anyway,
why, you know, why was it good for them? Everybody should have
that problem. How if you lose it for one can you use
it for another? How were they challenging רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon Ah,
but if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds that you can't redeem things
תמימים and they hold you could, then we understand why they're challenging.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says: "ממאי? Mimai? Who tells you that
that's what's going on? How does that work?" ממאי דרבי יהודה היא?
Mimai deRabbi Yehuda hi? What makes you think that the challenger of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically holds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that each קרבן korban does a different
function? והכי קאמר ליה. Vehachi ka'amar lei. Here's how they would read,
meaning: "If we agree to you, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon each קרבן
korban does a different function, but we understand why it works for
us to use one for another, we don't understand why it works
for you." Why would it work for them to use one for
another? הכי קאמר ליה, Hachi ka'amar lei, this is what they'd be
saying to him: "בשלמא לדידי דאמינא לב בית דין מתנה עליהם, Bishlama
ledidi de'amina Lev Beit Din matneh aleihem,
I get why even though I hold they all do slightly different
things, if you lose one you can use it for another, because
I hold that בית דין Beis Din. implicitly stipulates. אמטו להכי, Amtu
lehachi, once you concede that point, יקרבו, yikrevu, you can use one
for another. אלא לדידך דאמרת לא, Ella ledidach de'amart lo, but you,
you don't say בית דין stipulates, and therefore you can't just go
ahead if they're תמימים and change their status, so according to you
אמאי יקרבו? amai yikrevu? Why can they use one for the other?"
And his answer was, because they're all more or less טומאת מקדש.
tumat mikdash. Okay, that's one way of reading the debate, and then
it would have that the people that are taking it for granted
that you can use one for another is because לב בית דין
מתנה lev beit din matneh. עליהם. But that's not the only way
of reading the debate.
דילמא, Dilma, says the גמרא, Gemara רבי
מאיר היא. Rabbi Meir hi. Maybe the one challenging רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon's is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Remember רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says,
you know, יום כיפור, Yom Kippur רגלים, regalim, and ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, all do the exact same thing. They all do all the
same, all the whole set of variations of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash,
I don't have my chart up anymore. Anyway, so but maybe it's
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. והכי קאמר ליה, Vehachi ka'amar lei, this is
what he's telling him: "בשלמא לדידי דאמינא כל הני כפרה אחת היא,
Bishlama ledidi de'amina kol hanei kapara achat hi, according to me I
say all of the goats do the same thing, they all do
the same variations of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash, משום הכי יקרבו. Mishum
hachi yikrevu.
That's why if you lose one and you find it, you can
use it for the other one. Because they ממש mamash do the
same כפרה." kappara, This is a much better read of the challenge,
right? "אלא לדידך אמאי יקרבו? Ella ledidach amai yikrevu? For you, why
if you lose one can you use it for the other?" And
he says, "Yeah, they don't do the exact same thing, but close
enough." אלא, so fine. So now that we have that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon implicitly is saying you can't use one,
you don't say לב בית דין מתנה lev beit din matneh עליהם,
and we don't have any תנא Tanna who explicitly says you can
even in the case of like a קרבן, korban right? Outside of
פרה אדומה. Meaning we don't have any תנא Tanna that would say
you could do it when you could just simply choose to wait
for it to get a blemish. So now we've got a real
question. How does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. say his statement by the
תמידים, tmidim okay, if in that case maybe you can just wait
for it to get a blemish, and we don't know that any
תנא Tanna would say that point? So the גמרא Gemara says: "אלא
רבי יוחנן גמרא גמירי לה." Ella Rabbi Yochanan gemara gemiri lah. You're
right, he doesn't have an explicit תנא tanna that says it, he
just has a tradition. לדברי רבי שמעון אין נפדין לדברי חכמים נפדין.
Ledivrei Rabbi Shimon ein nifdin ledivrei chachamim nifdin. That's just his tradition.
So bottom line is that he basically had to concede that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of his position. He could not find
an explicit תנא who does hold. Yes, there are תנאים Tannaim that
agree with the basic mechanism of לב בית דין, Lev Beit Din,
but there's no תנא that explicitly applies. apply it to the case
of תמידים, tmidim? to the place of an animal where you could
just wait for it to get a blemish. And nevertheless, he is
asserting that that is his understanding, that that is a position of
the תנאים. tannaim. I suggest say that תוספות Tosfos points out that
he didn't really have to say רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagreed with
him. Maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does hold לב בית דין מתנה
עליהן, lev beis din masneh aleihen, but why do you need to
use that if you can basically just use one for another? Why
do you need to get בית דין stipulation involved? בית דין stipulation
is needed when you're stuck. So תוספות Tosfos asks that question what
forced רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to say that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
didn't agree with him. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon just says yeah you
can use it for one for the other, why do you need
to say לב בית דין? lev beis din? I didn't need to
say לב בית דין, lev beis din, I say they're all doing
more or less the same thing. It's not clear why the גמרא
Gemara felt that, but once רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan conceded that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon's didn't hold of his position, the גמרא Gemara sort
of made it clear that no תנא explicitly applies this idea of
לב בית דין lev beis din to a case of an unblemished
animal that you could just wait for it to get a blemish.
And nevertheless, that is רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan assertion. Yes, Charles?
There is at least one קרבן korban that magically becomes another type
of קרבן korban if it goes past which is the קרבן פסח
korban pesach if it goes past.
Right, so we're going to get to that. That's for an individual,
but we're talking about ציבור, tzibur, but we are going to get
to that issue which is a variation which is if you didn't
hold, and this is exactly going to be the סוגיא sugya of
the גמרא, Gemara if you didn't hold לב בית דין מתנה עליהן
lev beis din masneh aleihen or even if you did in principle
but you didn't want to apply it in every case,
what would happen by a קרבן korban. that it couldn't be used
for its original purpose? Would you have to, one option is wait
for it to get a מום mum and redeem it, but maybe
sometimes, similar to the way רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you can
use A for A-prime because they're close enough, maybe there's ways in
which a קרבן korban can be used for something else and slightly
change its identity. So that's what we're going to explore now. Putting
aside לב בית דין מתנה, lev beit din matneh if you're basically
stuck with it the way it is, other than waiting for it
to get a מום, mum, what are your other choices? So let's
take a look.
Is the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan accepted as הלכה halacha or the
רמב"ם? Rambam?
I don't know, I'd have to check the רמב"ם.
Rambam. The רמב"ם, Rambam, based on the letter says that it seems
like it is.
Right, because the גמרא Gemara seems to be operating with this, that's
always the question when the גמרא Gemara spends two דפים dappim operating
with a position, is that implicitly saying that it's buying into it
or it's implicitly saying that it's a דחוק dachuk position and it's
trying to use all of its efforts to reject it? That's why
learning is fun because you never know what the הלכה halacha is
going to be.
Exactly, the flimsy ground.
I do understand. It's also interesting why the גמרא Gemara. doesn't say
like רבי יוחנן תנא הוא. Rabbi Yochanan tanna hu.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was first generation אמוראים. Amoraim. So if the
גמרא Gemara. says
like רב תנא הוא ופליג, Rav tanna hu u'palig, I don't think
the גמרא Gemara says that too much by רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan
But anyway. All right, so let's take a look.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, I'm sorry.
גמר גמילי, gmar gmilei, fine. ולרבי שמעון דלית ליה לב בית דין
מתנה עליהן, u'l'Rabbi Shimon d'leisei lei lev beis din masneh aleihen, now
for רבי שמעון that doesn't hold of this position, this is going
to be a convenient way of asking what do you do when
you're stuck with a קרבן korban? in a certain position? מאי עבדינן
להו? mai avdinan lehu? What do you do with them? Now this
is not the question of the goat from יום כיפור Yom Kippur
got lost and you can use it for a regular ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh because there, although there's slight variations in the כפרה, it's
all from moneys of the same year. Now we've got a different
issue which is the תמידים temidim that were left over from last
year. It doesn't matter that it's the same thing, a תמיד tamid.
is a תמיד. tamid Oh so easy, just use it now,
now the third day of ניסן. Nissan. No, here there's a clear
line that you cannot use stuff from old moneys for the new
year. So now we've got a question, what do you do with
these old תמידים? temidim Now by the way תוספות Tosfos says that
this whole thing is just a לכתחילה, l'chatchila, בדיעבד b'dieved if you
were מקריב makriv it it would be good. Okay, but anyway, but
putting that aside, assuming that you can't redeem it because רבי שמעון
says you can't redeem it without a מום, mum, so you could
always wait until it gets a blemish, but the question is do
we have something we could do with this without waiting till it
gets a blemish? If it's last year's קרבן. korban. Let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי עבדינן להו, mai avdinan lehu,
what do we do with them? אמר רבי יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak amar Rabbi Yochanan מקיצין בהן את המזבח. makitzin bahen
es hamizbe'ach. Right, so Michael suggests along that you use it to
just for a סתם עולה, stam ola, nothing obligatory. It's a communal
מקיצין בהן את המזבח, makitzin bahen es hamizbe'ach, we're going to see
that the word comes from the word קיץ kayitz which the גמרא
Gemara says takes as a sense of dessert or summer vacation, which
is when the מזבח mizbe'ach is seeming to be on summer vacation
and not in use and there's a lull in the עבודה avoda
of the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. There's not a lot of traffic
today, it's a snowy day or whatever it is, that's not exactly
summer vacation. We'll just use this קרבן korban here to which it's
communal, it's not being brought by any individual but it's not fulfilling
any obligation and it's just to. know that we're still doing business
as usual, things are still up and running and so on. Okay,
that's the phrase of מקיצין בהן את המזבח. mekayitzin bahen et hamizbeach.
Now, the question is why can't it still be last year's קרבן?
korban. Even though it's just being used just to keep the מזבח
mizbeach active, it's still last year's קרבן. korban, How can you use
it? No, you do that every day don't you? Don't you do
that last day? No, that's not its answer. The answer is that
it's now the middle of ניסן Nissan or whatever it
is and we've had this
קרבן korban leftover from like אדר. Adar. So what are we gonna
do with it? So, oh, it's not so busy today, let's bring
it. Oh, but it's last year's קרבן. korban. Okay, so how does
that work? So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, let's
look at רש"י Rashi four lines down at the narrow lines.
That's what Michael said. But that doesn't of course, but let's say
it's a busy day today, then it's a waste like מקיצין בהן
את המזבח mekayitzin bahen et hamizbeach is like when we when otherwise
it wouldn't be operating and it keeps things looking
active.
So you're tagging this שעיר, se'ir, I mean whatever it is, a
sheep,
around like this, like how do you know which is which?
I guess you put some tag on it. Yeah, you get those
hospital tags, those are good. Okay, anyway,
בקיצור. Bekitzur. So let's
look at רש"י. Rashi. כשמזבח בטל מקריבין אותו עולות לנדבת ציבור keshemizbeach
battel makrivin oso olos lenedvas tzibur כדתנן לעיל בשמעתא דאמר מפרישין גבי
שעיר שלא קרב בזה יקרב בזה משום ד. kedesnan l'ail bishmata deamar
mafrishin gabei se'ir shelo karev bezeh yikarev bezeh mishum de. Anyway, let's
get to the fact that it's last year's money.
One minute.
Okay, oh that's the next line in the גמרא. Gemara I'm sorry.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara I thought it
was... Okay, so hold on one minute.
Okay, so I don't
see רש"י Rashi to say it explicitly, but the basic point here
is the following. The point is that when you have, okay, this
is a special הלכה. halacha. Let's say that actually, I forget the
fact that I brought the sheep with it. Here was all the
money I brought from last year.
Okay, was last year תשנ"ו? Tashnav? This was all my whatever תשנ"ו
Tashnav money. Okay, it's actually
תשנ"ז. Tashnaz. Wow, how time flies when you're having a fly. Okay,
anyway, here's my, it's not really helpful because you said the line
here is תשרי, Tishrei, but whatever, we're just going to assume that.
The
line is not תשרי, Tishrei, it's ניסן. Nissan. Okay, anyway, this is
last year's fine. One, two, three. That's confusing. This
is minus one, this is year one. There's no zero. Okay anyway,
whatever, it's like BCE and CE. There's no zero year. Anyway, this
is last year, this is this year. Okay, so we had this
money left over from last year. Forget that we had sheep left
over. We just had money left over. What do you do with
that money? Okay, that money was raised for buying קרבנות korbanot of
this year, of last year. You can't buy קרבנות korbanot of last
year. Redeem it on a פרוטה? perutah? No. So what do you
do with that money? So one of the things that you actually
do with that money is, and this is a special הלכה, halacha,
you are able to use it to buy קרבנות korbanot for
קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. So this money, last year's money, the actual
הלכה halacha is that you can now I have to draw a
sheep, because that'll be my wool. Okay, that's not bad. Not bad.
Okay, anyway, you can actually use that to bring the קרבנות korbanot
for קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbeach even for the next year. Okay, so
that's the הלכה halacha with last year's money. So now if you've
got last year's sheep, I've got to draw my wool again. If
you've got last year's sheep, okay, you know what you do with
it? No problem. You can't redeem it and you can't bring it
as a תמיד. tamid, It's just like last year's money and the
הלכה halacha is you can use last year's money to bring קרבנות
korbanos, for קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. Okay, so that's what you do
according to רבי שמעון with last year's sheep. You don't redeem it
and rebuy it and use it for this year's תמיד. tamid, You
treat it like last year's money and what you do is bring
קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. Yes, Charlie.
The ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh מוסף mussaf. includes seven lambs.
Right, but that's not good. Things that are like obligatory or whatever,
that has to be bought with this year's money. But things that
are נדבת ציבור nedvas tzibur can be bought with last year's money
and that's the... can it be a תמיד tamid, or not? Well,
it's not a תמיד, tamid, it's just an עולה. olah.
Just an עולה. olah. Last year's, didn't you put the money on
a פרוטה perutah like for מעשר שני Maaser Sheni then use it
for...? Yeah, you could.
We don't usually like to do unequal amounts or whatever and you
don't have to. There are things that that money's used...
those moneys are used for. Doesn't it go to קיץ המזבח kayitz
hamizbeach like
if he has extra money? Yeah, we'd rather not. It's seen as
like a little bit cheating הקדש hekdesh out of its money. Okay.
All right, so let's take a look. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
But don't you also use it... or maybe that's the fear, there's
too much money, that's what you also use it to like repair
the...?
Yes, you do. There's other things you do with it. Yes, exactly.
So yeah, there's all these other things. So not just. This is
one of the things you can do with it. Okay. Okay, so
let's take a look.
So now though, let's say what you had was, you had the
leftover קרבן, korban but you couldn't use it for the next מוסף.
mussaf? Why couldn't you use it for the next מוסף? mussaf Because
it became ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. So here you was
and you had this one here, this wasn't a תמיד, tamid this
was a goat. I can't draw a goat. Anyway, it's easier to
draw a sheep because I can just use the wool and put
a beard on it.
Okay. There's a goat.
I don't know what that looks like. Anyway, here it was, this
was the קרבן korban, for ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, okay,
last year. Now, if it was, you know, any other month, that's
רבי שמעון point, or from a רגל regel, to a ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh or יום כיפור Yom Kippur to ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh,
you could use it. But once you cross this line, you can't
use it for the מוסף musaf of this year, okay? Because it's
last year's קרבן. korban, That's a line that you don't cross. So
what do you do with it? And you don't bring it for
now. So you can't just say bring it for קיץ המזבח. kayitz
hamizbeach. That's only an עולה, olah, that's a freewill offering. A חטאת
chatas is an obligatory offering. So what are you able to do
with a חטאת? chatas? Okay. Nothing.
I mean חטאת. chatas.
Alright, but let's take a look. So the actually interesting הלכה halacha
is, if you wait for it to get a blemish and you
redeem it, what do you think you can do with its money?
Make another חטאת? chatas?
Well, then it becomes like last year's money. It has the קדושה
kedusha of last year's money. So if it actually gets a blemish
and you redeem it, you can use that money to buy an
עולה olah for קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. You could do that. So
since that's where this is heading, its value is heading, it's on
that track, okay, why not just bring it for קיץ המזבח? kayitz
hamizbeach? Yes, it has קדושה kedusha of a
חטאת, chatas, because קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbeach doesn't it make a difference
what קרבן korban, it is, a כבש keves or a goat of
the year?
No, an עולה olah can be either. Okay? So yes, it's a
חטאת, chatas, but once it gets a blemish, you're going to be
able to redeem it and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, and now
you might say maybe you're not allowed to use that money after
you redeem it, maybe it's חטאת chatas money or whatever. Okay. Yes,
it's a very reasonable thing to think. Okay, but take a look,
I have to remind you though what we do, look at the
top of י"א עמוד ב'. Okay, look at the top of י"א
עמוד ב'. It says like this: רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rabbi
Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon omrim, third line from the top, ירעו עד שיסתאבו.
yiru ad sheyistavu. This is exactly about what happens about שירי, shirei,
about חטאות chataos that got lost and rediscovered. וימכרו ויפלו דמיהם לנדבה.
v'yimachru v'yipelu dmeihem l'nedavah. They exactly say that what you do by
a חטאת ציבור chatas tzibur is you redeem it, you use the
money to bring an עולה, olah, a freewill עולה, olah, a communal
freewill עולה olah on the מזבח. mizbeach. So that's actually a הלכה.
halacha. By a personal חטאת, chatas, right, you'd have to let it
die. But by a communal חטאת, chatas, you redeem it and the
money goes to buy an עולה. olah. So according to them, but
working within that, if that's where this is going, maybe we should
just be able to just bring this straight as an עולה olah
since that's where it's headed anyway. Okay? Of course then nothing changed
its status, so you sort of understand the problem with that. So
let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. ומודה
רבי שמעון בסיומי חטאת שאין מקיצין בגופן אלא בדמיהן. u'modeh Rabbi Shimon
b'siyumei chatas she'ein mikesit b'gufan ela bidmeihen. There, you can't use them
themselves. Yes, it's true. A חטאת ציבור chatas tzibur that wasn't used,
you redeem it and you know, that's before, that's when it gets
a blemish. Okay. So, but so here why not say why do
you need, and then you would use it for an עולה. olah.
So why not say here, why wait for it to get a
blemish? Just use it straight. If you can use last year's sheep
for this year's עולה olah for this year's עולה olah as a
קיץ המזבח, kayitz hamizbeach, not as a תמיד, tamid, say the same
with the goat. No, that you can't. הכא והכא, hacha v'hacha, you
say you can, is that what the point?
You can once it gets a blemish and you redeem it. But
you can't do the thing itself. Okay. So,
wait a minute, where is it? אלא בדמיהן הכא הוא דמעיקרא עולה
והשתא עולה. ela bidmeihen hacha hu d'me'ikara olah v'hashta olah. In this
case, it was brought, it was sanctified as an עולה, olah, yes
for a תמיד, tamid, and now it's still going to be an
עולה, olah, so it's basically the same thing. And it is true
that it's last year's, but since it's only קיץ המזבח, kayitz hamizbeach,
that's okay, even though it's last year's. Okay. But here, you need
to change its identity. It's a חטאת. chatas. Without it getting a
blemish and redeeming it or whatever, nothing is going to change its
חטאת, chatas, its identity. Alright. So fine, because it's last year's, you
are still allowed to use it this year as קיץ המזבח, kayitz
hamizbeach, but you have to get it to stop being a חטאת.
chatas. You've got to wait for it to get a blemish.
Okay. אבל חטאת דמעיקרא חטאת והשתא עולה. aval chatas d'me'ikara chatas v'hashta
olah. It started as a חטאת chatas and now it's going to
be an עולה. olah. גזירה לאחר כפרה אטו לפני כפרה. gezeirah l'achar
kapparah atu lifnei kapparah. We can't, now this is interesting. You would
expect the גמרא Gemara would say there's not a גזירה, gezeirah, this
is a real הלכה halacha that it doesn't change its identity until
it gets a blemish and until you do so. to change its
identity from a חטאת chatas to an עולה. ola. This גמרא Gemara
makes it sound like once the circumstances have dictated that it can
no longer be brought as a חטאת, chatas, and once clearly the
path it's on is to be get a blemish and be redeemed
and get an עולה ola etc., then that already changes its status
automatically. And the only reason you can't use that goat automatically, since
eventually its moneys are going to go to an עולה, ola, it
really technically is an עולה ola and really in theory you could
use it. But if we let you do that, you might come
to go ahead and use a goat for an עולה ola even
when it's still fit to be used as a חטאת. chatas. You
might use it let's say before the next year when you could
still use this for like, you know, well I guess if it's
אדר Adar there's no ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh left, but anyway. You
know what I'm saying, but even when it still has the possibility
of serving as a חטאת, chatas, you might say hey I remember
last time we had some חטאת chatas that we lost and found
again and we used as an עולה, ola, and let's do it
this time. Okay, so because that's risky that that this only works
after something else was brought in its place and this no longer
has the potential of being brought as a חטאת, chatas, we don't
want to let you use the thing itself because you might get
it confused, right you understand? The reason this thing now is standing
for an עולה ola is two reasons. Number one, it wasn't used
for its own purpose, something else was brought by mistake by but
in its stead because this thing got lost and it's too late,
it's after ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. So it's saying even
though in theory we can we want you to redeem it and
so on because there are cases where where those circumstances are not
in place and it still is fixed its identity as a חטאת.
chatas. Now תוספות Tosafot says that other גמרות Gemarot make it sound
pretty clear that it's not just a גזירה. gezeirah. Other גמרות Gemarot
make it sound like it does not change its identity from a
חטאת chatas to an עולה ola unless something concrete happens to it.
It might be a blemish. Another גמרא Gemara really sounds like it's
one stage before— wait a minute,
a blemish it can't be used for anything, right?
No, then you redeem it and then you whatever. I'm saying that
okay, but but other גמרות Gemarot make it— but a case where
you could use the thing itself but still it doesn't happen automatically
automatically is the גמרא Gemara says ניתק לרעייה. nitak lire'iyah. If you
basically take this goat and you say alright, this is a חטאת,
chatas, it's last year's, we can't use it. We're going to put
it in this pen and wait for it to get a blemish
and then we'll redeem it and use the money for an עולה.
ola. Once you have done something concrete and set it out for
pasture waiting for it to get a blemish, okay, then you clearly
put it on that path, then it changes its identity as an
עולה. ola. But it doesn't just happen automatically. All right, so our
גמרא Gemara is a little strange because our גמרא Gemara sounds like
it happens automatically. Right, but just to repeat, your your sheep from
last— your moneys from last year can be used for קיץ המזבח
kayitz hamizbei'ach for this year. Your sheep from last year for a
תמיד tamid can be used for קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbei'ach for this
year. עולה ola עולה ola same thing. The fact that it's last
year this year— well last year it was a תמיד, tamid, here
it's only קיץ המזבח, kayitz hamizbei'ach, we're a little more flexible by
קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbei'ach. Your last year's goat cannot be used for
קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbei'ach because last year's goat was a חטאת. chatas.
Okay, and it doesn't just change its identity automatically. So in that
case, you basically have to wait for it to get a blemish,
use the money and buy קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbei'ach. The גמרא Gemara
makes it sound though that in principle you really could use it
for קיץ המזבח, kayitz hamizbei'ach, but it's too easy to get confused,
but that's a little strange to think that it changes its identity
so you know without anything concrete having been done. Yes.
Something like the תמידים temidim where they had a whole bunch of
backups for the שעירים se'irim they didn't have any?
That's an interesting question. Did they spend— that that's correct. No the
reason they had backups for the תמידים temidim. is that they weren't
backups, is that they were because you're always bringing two a day.
So they're checking them over a four day period. So for the
goats also in the מוספין musafin they would have a— they would
buy the goat four days in advance and check it for four
days. But they had extra תמידים temidim not as backups but just
because
you're always bringing you know every single day. So if you need
four days in advance you're always going to have a certain amount
of תמידים. Okay, all right.
Now and then— anyway this case though is when it got lost
and you brought another one.
Yes. Yes. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, אף אנן נמי תנינא,
af anan nami tanina, we talk similarly. פר ושעיר של יום הכיפורים
שאבדו והפריש אחרים תחתיהם, par vese'ir shel Yom HaKippurim she'avdu vehefrish acherim
tachtehem, you have the goat and the cow on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur that got lost and you other ones were brought in their
stead. וכן שעיר עבודת כוכבים שאבדו והפריש אחרים תחתיהם, vechein se'ir avodat
kochavim she'avdu vehefrish acherim tachtehem, is just what we quoted yesterday.
כולם ימותו דברי רבי יהודה, kulam yamutu divrei Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says okay, it's
a חטאת שנתכפרו בעליה, chatas shenitkapru ba'aleha, and you let it die.
רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים ירעו עד שיסתאבו וימכרו ויפלו דמיהם לנדבה
שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. Rabbi Elazar veRabbi Shimon omrim yire'u ad sheyista'avu
veyimakru veyipilu demeihen linedavah she'ein chatas tzibbur meisah. No,
you wait till it gets a blemish, you redeem it, you use
the money to buy a עולה, ola, and that's what you do
with it. So basically what we've been saying except in that case
it is not last year's קרבן, korban, it's this year's קרבן, korban.
but nevertheless you know because it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur you can't
use it for anything else and since you can't use it— it
for another type of a חטאת, chatas, this is what you have
to do with it. They don't hold this הלכה halacha of letting
the חטאת chatas die applies to a communal חטאת. chatas. They hold
by a communal חטאת, chatas, if there's nothing you can do with
it, you let it get a blemish, you redeem it, you use
the money to bring an עולה. olah. שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. She-ein
chatas tzibur mesah. ואמאי? Ve-amai? Now, why did they have to go
through the whole blemish road? נקרבו אינו גופיה? Nikrevu inu gufeih? As
long as its moneys are going to bringing an עולה, olah, just
bring it as an עולה. olah. נקרבו אינו גופיה עולה? Nikrevu inu
gufeih olah? אלא לאו שמע מינה Ella lav shema mina גזירה לאחר
כפרה אטו לפני כפרה. gezeirah le-achar kapparah atu lifnei kapparah. You see
that we do not allow because because if we in well again,
this גמרא Gemara is saying like in principle you're right, we could
bring this as an עולה, olah, but then you'll come to bring
it as an עולה olah even when it could still be brought
as a חטאת, chatas, even when something wasn't brought in its stead
and it's still able to be brought as a חטאת. chatas. So
because we don't want you to do that, it's only works now
as an עולה olah because the ability for it to be as
a חטאת chatas has been shut off, you know, closed off. That's
why it's changed its identity. But that's you know, so but that's
easy to confuse those cases, so that's why we're going to demand
that you redeem it. Again, I'd rather the גמרא Gemara said a
more principled reason like it doesn't change its identity automatically. Okay, that's
the easier reason to explain. Yes, Jenna.
But that would be problematic with some other ones also, right, if
you brought them for something else? Like that ones, I mean I
know that has to do with the timing out.
What are you saying, what other ones?
The sheep and the this?
Yeah, but this you are bringing for something else. It was sanctified
as a תמיד, Tamid, and because now it's last year's קרבן, korban,
you bring it this year for קיץ המזבח. kayitz ha-mizbeiach. But it's
עולה olah עולה, olah, so it's not really. So while it's changing
its חיוב ציבור chiyuv tzibur and a תמיד tamid, as opposed to
a נדבת ציבור. nidvas tzibur.
But because it has it in like the next year you and.
Oh, oh I see your point. Your point is let's say it
was still this year and it was wandering around and I accidentally
and I said, oh you know what? I know it's set aside
for tomorrow's תמיד, tamid, but today's a slow day, let's bring it
for קיץ המזבח. kayitz ha-mizbeiach.
I might think it would be more like right, would that be
good בדיעבד? bedieved? That חטאת chatas is good. Like okay, it's an
עולה olah and was brought for קיץ. kayitz. So okay, you're right,
you might do that, but then it's an עולה, olah, you know.
Here if you bring it when it's still a חטאת chatas and
you bring it for an עולה, olah, it's invalid. Right, so that's
exactly it. But yes, good point. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר רב אשי אף אנן נמי תנינא, Amar Rav
Ashi af anan nami tanina, you another proof, another משנה. Mishnah והשני
ירעה עד שיסתאב. Ve-hasheni yireh ad she-yista-ev. This is what happens when
you lose one of the two goats, you know, one going לעזאזל
la-Azazel and the other going inside and one of them gets lost
or dies or gets a מום, mum, so you bring another pair.
But if you bring another pair, then you're going to have an
extra goat going around there. So what do you do with the
extra goat? So you let it graze till it gets a blemish,
וימכר ויפלו דמיו לנדבה. ve-yimacher ve-yipelu damav linedavah. You use the money
for an עולה. olah. ואמאי יקרבו אינו גופיה עולה? Ve-amai yikrevu inu
gufeih olah? Why don't you use it for an עולה? olah? It's
a חטאת chatas of יום כיפור Yom Kippur. that you can't use
for anything else. So once its moneys are going towards an עולה,
olah, use it itself. אלא לאו שמע מינה Ella lav shema mina
גזירה לאחר כפרה אטו לפני כפרה. gezeirah le-achar kapparah atu lifnei kapparah.
We don't allow even though now it's already atoned, meaning you know
something else is atoned in its place, we don't let you use
it for an עולה olah itself because you'll come to wind up
doing that even when it still could be used as a חטאת.
chatas. Again, I so wish the גמרא Gemara had said because you
need something concrete to change its identity. Anyway, okay, תוספות Tosafos discusses
that, okay. This גמרא Gemara is very strange that it makes it
such a secondary reason why not to do this. אמר רבינא אף
אנן נמי תנינא, Amar Ravina af anan nami tanina, we also taught
that way. אשם שמתו בעליו, Asham she-mesu be-alav, או שנתכפרו בעליו. o
she-nitkapru be-alav.
So now, similar to what we've just said about a communal חטאת,
chatas, we say about an אשם. asham. What happens, an אשם asham
is brought by a sin? So there's always one opinion in the
of the תנאים Tanna'im that it's just like a חטאת, chatas, and
if it got lost and they found another and they brought another
one or whatever, then the same way you let the original חטאת
chatas die, you let the original אשם asham die. But the other
opinion is no, אשם asham has a different הלכה. halacha. What's its
different הלכה? halacha? If you lost the אשם, asham, you brought another
one, you found the first one, just like we're saying about a
communal חטאת, chatas, you wait till it gets a blemish, you use
the money to buy an עולה. olah. This is not an עולת
ציבור, olas tzibur, I lost my אשם, asham, so if I now
found it and I'm going to redeem it whatever, I'm going to
bring my personal קרבן, korban, so what I'm going to do with
the moneys is I'm going to bring a personal עולה. olah. But
other than the difference between עולה olah and ציבור, tzibur, they're both
the same idea, you bring an עולה olah that's not obligatory. Okay,
but again, this is only after it gets a blemish. I can't
automatically just use it for that even though it no longer is
needed for my original חטאת. chatas. אשם שמתו בעליו, Asham she-mesu be-alav,
the owners died, או שנתכפרו בעליו, o she-nitkapru be-alav, or they atoned
or their atonement was through another קרבן. korban ירעה עד שיסתאב, yireh
ad she-yista-ev, let it graze until it gets a blemish, וימכר ויפלו
דמיו לנדבה, ve-yimacher ve-yipelu damav linedavah, you use the money for a
נדבה. nedavah. רבי אליעזר אומר ימות, Rabbi Eliezer omer yamut, no, Rabbi
Eliezer basically says it's like a חטאת, chatas, you have to let
it die. רבי יהושע אומר יביא בדמיו עולה, Rabbi Yehoshua omer yavi
bedamav olah, bring an עולה. olah. Now, what's the difference between עולה
olah and נדבה? nedavah?
Wait, didn't you say Rabbi Elazar was the same? Rabbi Elazar before.
That's רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, this is אליעזר. Eliezer. Okay, anyway, so
the only difference between Rabbi Yehoshua who says יביא בדמיו עולה yavi
bedamav olah and the original
יפלו דמיו לנדבה yipelu damov linedavah means נדבת ציבור. nidvas tzibbur. So
according to the first opinion, it's ממש mamash the same as the
case of the חטאת ציבור. chatas tzibbur. Even though it's my personal
אשם, asham, once I can no longer use it, I transfer the
קדושה kedushah to the קדושה kedushah to money after it gets a
blemish and I give that money to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and they use it for their קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbeach fund. Okay,
whereas the final opinion, רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says no, I get
to bring my own personal עולה olah with it. יביא בדמיו עולה.
Yavi bidamov olah. קיץ המזבח Kayitz hamizbeach means... Yeah,
especially the phrase יפלו דמיו לנדבה. yipelu damov linedavah. יפלו דמיו Yipelu
damov means the money gets thrown to, like gets contributed to the
נדבה nedavah fund, the קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbeach fund. Okay, okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. וליקרב הוא גופיה, Uleikrav hu gufei, וליקרב הוא גופיה, uleikrav hu
gufei, why not bring it itself? So עולה? olah? So אמר ליה,
Amar lei, גזירה לאחר כפרה אטו לפני כפרה, gezeirah le'acher kapparah atu
lifnei kapparah, שמע מינה, shma mina,
good point. Okay. So now what we said is you have leftover
funds, use it for קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. You have leftover sheep,
even though they were תמיד, tamid. use it for קיץ המזבח. kayitz
hamizbeach. You have leftover goats that were a חטאת, chatas, even though
the הלכה halacha is you wait for it to get a blemish,
you redeem it and then it magically transfers into עולה olah for,
you know, now that it's not about the animal itself, it's more
abstract. The הלכה halacha is a חטאת chatas that can't be brought,
a חטאת ציבור chatas tzibbur that can't be brought and an אשם
asham that can't be brought, the moneys can go to an עולה.
olah. And even though it was last year's, you can bring it
this year for a קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. But you have to
wait for it to get a blemish. It doesn't happen automatically. The
גמרא Gemara makes it a גזירה gezeirah reason. Maybe there's a more
reason that you actually need something concrete to change its identity. So
for the חטאת, chatas, you cannot bring the thing itself. Yes, Charlie?
So this is a rare case for הקדש hekdesh to lose, because
הקדש hekdesh has to pay for the cost of grazing the animal
until it's developed a blemish?
Yeah, but they would probably put it in a pen that had
a lot of barbed wire around it. Alright, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Exactly.
Well, okay. So now the גמרא says like this. Okay. שמע מינה.
תניא נמי הכי. Shma mina. Tanya nami hachi. Now, we taught similarly
to not just this thing about the חטאת, chatas, the goat, the
חטאת chatas having to transfer the money, but the general idea that
the leftover moneys here can be used. I think this רש"י Rashi
at the end was רש"י Rashi I was looking for before. If
you look two lines from the bottom on רש"י, Rashi, תניא נמי
הכי, tanya nami hachi, כי אמר אל מותרות רבי
שמעון, ki amar el mosros Rebbi Shimon, leftover moneys from last year,
מקיצין בהם את המזבח. mekitzin bahem es hamizbeach. That one of the
things you can do with last year's leftover money, money, was this
קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. Okay. How do you know this? מה הן
מביאין מן המותרות? Mah hen mevi'in min hamosros?
Here's exactly the question. What do you bring with the leftover funds?
So this is not the question of the leftover קרבנות, korbanos just
the leftover moneys collected from last year. What do you do with
them? אה, קיץ, קיץ. Ah, kayitz, kayitz. כבנות שוח למזבח. Kibnos shuach
lamizbeach. You bring some type of, like רש"י Rashi says, קיץ kayitz
is like a dessert, a delicacy, like these בנות שוח bnos shuach
which are a particular type of a date or something or whatever
they are. Fig, are they a fig? You know, you offer them,
you, like it's a little treat for the מזבח. mizbeach. A little
ketchup, a little ice cream for the מזבח, mizbeach, that's what you
give it for. Okay.
Now there's a long תוספות Tosafos because he says some גמרות Gemaros
make it sound like this בנות שוח bnos shuach is a very
tasty fig, others make it sound like it's a non-edible thing. So
whatever, תוספות Tosafos trying to figure out what these בנות שוח bnos
shuach are.
What do you mean? When do we put things on the altar?
I know, that's what תוספות Tosafos says. וכתיב כי כל שאור וכל
דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה', Uksiv ki chol se'or vechol devash
lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem, right? So don't put, what do you
mean? You don't put the ice cream and figs on the altar.
תני רבי חנינא: כבנות שוח אדם. Tani Rebbi Chanina: kibnos shuach adam.
No, the same way a person would like to have a little
fig or whatever, you know, as a little midday snack because you're
going six hours you're not eating anything, so you get a little...
alright, so we put a little עולה olah on the מזבח, mizbeach,
keep it busy, keep it happy. Okay. רב נחמן בר רב חסדא,
Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda, fine. אין מקיצין בעולת העוף. Ein mekitzin
be'olas ha'of. Now that we're talking about this general phenomenon about keeping
the מזבח mizbeach active, he says one of the things you do
not do with it, you might bring a sheep or goat or
whatever you bring as an עולה, olah, but you do not bring
a bird עולה. olah. Why not? So אמר רבא: הא בורכא. Amar
Rava: Ha burcha. Ah, that's made up. You're just making that up.
Why is that? So אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא, Amar
lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak leRava, מאי בורכא? mai burcha?
Why are you saying it's nonsense? אנא אמריתה ניהליה, Ana amrisah nihaleih,
I was the one who told it to רב נחמן בר רב
חסדא. Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda.
ומשמיה דרב שימי מנהרדעא אמריתה ניהליה, Umeshamei deRav Shimi miNeharde'a amrisah nihaleih,
and just so you know who's saying this, in the name of
רב שימי מנהרדעא, Rav Shimi miNeharde'a, presumably that name meant something to
רבא. Rava. דאמר רב שימי מנהרדעא: מותרות, De'amar Rav Shimi miNeharde'a: mosros,
leftover moneys from last year, לנדבת ציבור אזלי, lenidvas tzibbur azli, they
have to go to a communal, the nature of the עולה olah
has to be a communal עולה. olah. Okay. ואין עולת העוף בציבור.
Ve'ein olas ha'of b'tzibbur. So here's the reason. An עולת עוף olat
of can only be brought by an individual, and this has to
be a communal offering, it's by communal funds. Well, if that's true,
it's a pretty darn good reason. Wonder why רבא Rava mocked it.
That's a pretty, that's not even
a complicated explanation. These are communal sacrifices, okay. Now, maybe he disagreed
with the idea of אין עולת ציבור, ein olat tzibur, you know,
that there's no such thing as an עולת ציבור olat tzibur as
an עולת עוף olat of that, excuse me,
a ציבור tzibur cannot bring an עולת עוף. olat of. We learn
it because by the עולת עוף, olat of, by the עולת עוף
olat of it says נפש כי תקריב. nefesh ki takriv. So I
think רש"י Rashi says, and therefore we emphasize that it means it's
only brought by an individual and not by the ציבור. tzibur. Let
me see if רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק. pasuk. ויקריב מן התורים,
ve-hikriv min ha-torim,
no, just
ויקריב, ve-hikriv, את קרבנו, et korbano, no, not נפש. nefesh. נפש nefesh
is by a מנחה. mincha. את קרבנו. et korbano. So somehow because
it emphasizes קרבנו, korbano, his personal קרבן, korban okay, that's why he
says that it only can be brought by an individual, can't be
brought by a ציבור. tzibur. But
תוספות, Tosafot, I was thinking about תוספות. Tosafot. Look at תוספות. Tosafot.
Because תוספות Tosafot actually questions how black and white this הלכה halacha
is. Because if this הלכה halacha were black and white, you don't
understand why רבא Rava was mocking it, right? Clearly we're dealing with
a communal sacrifice. So look at תוספות. Tosafot. ואין
עולת עוף בציבור, ve-ein olat of be-tzibur, משום דכתיב ביה נפש, mishum
de-chtiv beih nefesh, דמשמע ביחיד. de-mashma be-yachid. I don't know which פסוק
pasuk he's referring to. Anyway, דווקא. davka. Michael, you can try to
remind us, okay. ואם תאמר, ve-im tomar, ואמר בפרק טרף בקלפי, ve-amar
be-perek teref be-kalphi, זבין פרידה אחת אף עולה זבין אזלו לנדבה, zavin
perida achat af olah zavin azlu le-nedavah, ויש לומר דאין לקנות עוף
במוותרות שנותרו. ve-yesh lomar de-ein liknot of be-motarot she-notru. You're not supposed
to use the money. אכן קרבו לפנינו, achen karvu lefaneinu, if we
actually have a bird that was bought for that purpose, בקיצין בו,
be-ketzin bo, דמאי יפה ממנו, de-mai yafeh mimenu, what else are you
supposed to do with it? We'd just maybe let it die? I
don't know. Anyway, so the point is, the only reason I had
you see that תוספות Tosafot was to understand if it really, the
הלכה halacha was really that black and white that you can never
bring a communal עולת עוף, olat of, it's really bizarre that רבא
Rava was mocking the point, okay. So תוספות Tosafot at least points
out maybe בדיעבד bedi'avad you could. But anyway, this is his answer.
The answer is, the reason you do not use the money for
that is because at least לכתחילה, lechatchila, you're certainly not, a bird
עולה olah is only supposed to be a private עולה, olah, not
a communal one.
וזה שמואל סבר לה כרבי
יוחנן.
ve-zeh Shmuel savar lah ke-Rabbi
Yochanan.
Now, שמואל Shmuel also holds of רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan, position. Remember,
רבי יוחנן's position was about the תמידים that you can redeem it
later, לב בית דין מתנה עליהן, lev beit din matneh aleihen, etc.
Let's see why he holds of it. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל:
de-amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibur, סכין מושכתן למה
שהן. sakin moshechtan lama she-hen. The קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibur, the knife
drags them to what they are. So what does this mean?
Okay, so if you look at רש"י, Rashi, right, רש"י Rashi explains
the following: סכין השוחטתן סתם מושכתן לקרבן שהופרש מתחילה לכך, sakin ha-shochettan
stam moshechtan le-korban she-hufrash mi-tchila le-kach, ואפילו אין זה
קרבן עצמו. ve-afilu ein zeh korban atzmo. So basically what רש"י Rashi
says it's coming to prove, and the reason I'm reading this is
that תוספות Tosafot disagrees, okay, is that even though we're talking about
the idea that that this
sheep that's slaughtered now the next year, the same sheep itself can
be used for
קיץ המזבח. keitz ha-mizbe'ach. Alright? Why? So he says you see this
from this phrase that a communal sacrifice, the knife defines their identity.
Okay, so the knife defines their identity means even though it was
a תמיד, because it's as long as it's a reasonable identity to
give it, it's being brought this year, this is now what it's
going to serve, but I'll read you in a minute how תוספות
Tosafot reads it. Yeah, Michael.
This is a question, we learned this before, but we have before
that אשם שמתו בעליו, asham she-metu ba'alav, one of the positions, we
have three of them, was that I can actually myself bring it
as an עולה? olah? Meaning that, you know, I transfer the money
and bring an עולה, olah, right? So can that, does that have
to be a כבש keves or can that one be an
עולת עוף? olat of?
Wait, one more time, say it again?
Before we had אשם שמתו בעליו asham she-metu ba'alav or שנתכפרו בעליו,
she-nitkapru ba'alav, yeah, and then there were three
positions: עד שיסתאב, adei she-yista'ev, and then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said
ימות, yamut, and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said יביא בדמיו
עולה.
yavi
bi-damaiv olah. So can that, does that עולה olah have to be
any kind of עולה? olah? Can that be an עולת עוף, olat
of, the personal one?
Oh, presumably, yes.
Okay, just to see.
Yeah, yeah. Okay, so now according to רש"י, Rashi, this is supporting
not רבי יוחנן's original statement about לב בית דין מתנה עליהן, lev
beit din matneh aleihen, etc., but this is supporting רבי יוחנן's statement,
right, remember רבי יוחנן's original statement that you can redeem them without
a blemish? This is supporting רבי יוחנן's statement that for רבי שמעון
who doesn't hold of redeeming without a blemish, you can use last
year's sheep for this year's קיץ המזבח. keitz ha-mizbe'ach. I'll tell you
in a minute how תוספות Tosafot reads it. Let's just read the
next line.
תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly: ומודה רבי שמעון
בשעיר שלא קרב ברגל יקרב בראש
חודש. u-modeh Rabbi Shimon be-sa'ir she-lo karev ba-regel yikarev be-rosh chodesh. רבי
שמעון agrees that if the goat, this is רבי שמעון's idea, you
can use a goat for the רגלים regalim for ראש חודש, rosh
chodesh, etc., if it wasn't... If you didn't bring it for one
רגל, regel, bring it on ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. אם לא קרב
ברגל זה, Im lo karev baregel zeh, יקרב ברגל אחר. yikarev baregel
acher. If you didn't bring it for one רגל, regel. did I
skip a line? ואם לא קרב בראש, V'im lo karev b'rosh, sorry,
ואם לא קרב בראש חודש, v'im lo karev b'Rosh Chodesh, יקרב ביום
הכיפורים. yikarev b'Yom HaKippurim.
If it's not ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, then יום כיפור. Yom Kippur
ואם לא קרב ביום הכיפורים, V'im lo karev b'Yom HaKippurim, Michael just
wait, יקרב ברגל, yikarev baregel, bring it on the רגל. regel ואם
לא קרב ברגל זה, V'im lo karev baregel zeh, יקרב ברגל אחר.
yikarev baregel acher. שמתחילה לא בא אלא לכפר על מזבח החיצון, She'mitechilah
lo ba ela l'chaper al mizbeach hachitzon,
because originally it was only coming for the outer מזבח, mizbeach, meaning
and therefore since it was all coming as a מוסף musaf, on
the outer מזבח mizbeach as opposed to the inner one on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur. and it was all coming for roughly the same
reason, for טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash, if you don't use it for
one you can use it for the other. Now how does this
support the idea of what does this exactly supporting? This is the
רבי שמעון that we know. So רש"י Rashi says what it's supporting
is that since it's the idea that if it was designated for
one קרבן, korban it can be brought for a slightly different one
as long as it's roughly the same, so the same is true
here that if it was designated for last year's תמיד, it could
be brought for this year's קיץ המזבח. ka'itz hamizbeach. Not exactly the
same but they're close enough. Okay, fine, that's all very nice but
then you could have just quoted רבי שמעון in the משנה. Mishnah
What's the point of quoting this? So תוספות Tosafot brings down an
explanation which he doesn't like but I like a lot, it's because
it's the one that I thought of before I read תוספות, Tosafot,
which is that if you look closely what exactly is the order
that רבי שמעון is giving? He says if it was not קרב
ברגל, karev baregel, what's the first רגל regel for the תנאים? Tannaim?
Not סוכות, Sukkot, the first רגל regel is פסח. Pesach. If it
wasn't brought for פסח, Pesach, יקרב בראש חודש. yikarev b'Rosh Chodesh. Okay,
so
יקרב בראש חודש. yikarev b'Rosh Chodesh. ואם לא קרב בראש חודש, V'im
lo karev b'Rosh Chodesh, יקרב ביום הכיפורים. yikarev b'Yom HaKippurim. Okay, well
wait, actually we skipped שבועות. But anyway, I don't know why we
skipped it. Anyway, so now it's all the way יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur, ואם לא קרב ביום הכיפורים, V'im lo karev b'Yom HaKippurim, יקרב
ברגל. yikarev baregel. What's the רגל regel now that we're talking about?
סוכות. Sukkot. ואם לא קרב ברגל זה, V'im lo karev baregel zeh,
יקרב ברגל אחר. yikarev baregel acher. What was the רגל regel after
סוכות? Sukkot? Not פסח Pesach yet,
it's שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. Okay, so in that case, now why
doesn't he say why does he stop there? Why does he stop
there? Because the next thing, now okay there's more ראש חודשים Rosh
Chodeshim coming, but the next רגל regel, that's coming is already the
new moneys, it's after ניסן. Nissan. Okay, so since he stopped there,
it's clear that according to him, that goat you can't carry over
into the next year. Okay, so that's supporting the claim of רבי
יוחנן, right, that from the goat from last year and he doesn't
say יקרב תמימים. yikarev tmimim. It also supports that idea, right? It
sounds like you're just sort of like stuck, right, that that goat
anyway. So like that's a different way of reading that. Yes.
It's going to be interesting that
I guess I understand the but according to some opinions this may
all be for the same thing, they're all טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash.
but you also kind of think, I just like to be thinking
outside. You also like to designate like a
יום כיפור קרבן. Yom Kippur korban. Or he designates the קרבן korban
to do this specific purpose. You designate like a יום כיפור קרבן
Yom Kippur korban and...
Okay, well that's part of רבי שמעון's חידוש. Rabbi Shimon's chidush. Okay,
anyway, I get it. So I just want to do one final
explanation about what the whole חידוש chidush here of סכין מושכתן sakin
moshachtan is. Look at the second wide line of תוספות. Tosafot. The
תוספות Tosafot אף שמואל סבר, af Shmuel savar, but the second wide
line of the widest line. He says ונראה כפירוש הערוך, v'nir'eh k'ferush
he'Aruch, דפירש סכין מושכתן למחשיהם, depirash sakin moshachtan l'machsheihem, אם תמידים אם
מוספים סכין מושכתן להיות כן, im tmimim im musafim sakin moshachtan l'hiyot
ken, דטרם מושכם לסכין אין לומר איזה תמיד איזה מוסף, d'terem moshcham
lasakin ein lomar eizeh tamid eizeh musaf, אלא תלויים ועומדים בתנאי לב
בית דין. ela tluyim v'omdim bitnai lev beit din. Michael, this is
for you, because Michael asked can you sanctify a קרבן korban somewhat
generically? So let's say I have a sheep and I'm just going
to sanctify it and because it's today is I don't know, it's
פסח, Pesach, there's a lot of things this sheep could be. Well
not a lot, whatever, there's a lot of sheep in the מוסף,
there's a sheep for the תמיד. So which one is it? So
can I just sort of make it generic and say, right, that
when I get around to שחיטה shechitah it, whichever קרבן korban I
use it for, that'll be the קרבן korban it is. Okay, so
that's the way תוספות Tosafot reads this idea of that the knife
drags it. That the knife, you are allowed to have a generic
status and the knife sort of can define more precisely what that
status is. Okay? And תוספות Tosafot says that that's like similar to
the idea of לב בית דין מתנה. lev beit din matneh You
understand how it's similar to the idea of... before we said לב
בית דין מתנה lev beit din matneh more radically. You brought it
for a קרבן korban and now it's for בדק הבית. bedek habayit.
But here the לב בית דין מתנה is like, we're going to
use this sheep for some קרבן korban today. We'll figure it out
when we get to it. All right, and then when you actually
שוחט shochet it, then its identity is solidified. Okay? And that also
a little bit is consistent with רבי שמעון's idea, although רבי שמעון
doesn't agree with לב בית דין מתנה radically. It's a little consistent
with this idea that if it wasn't used for the יום כיפור
מוסף, Yom Kippur musaf, it could be used for a רגל, regel,
and if it wasn't used for a רגל, it could be used
for ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. They're all roughly the same. So this
is a similar idea to the לב בית דין
מתנה that within a range of possibilities how you שוחט shochet it...
defines what its identity is. Yes. So a little simple question. If
I point at a sheep and say זו עולה Zo olah or
זו שלמים, Zo shlamim, it comes out? Who has the authority to
declare that an animal is a communal חטאת Chatas or communal תמידין?
Temidin? I mean, who is the person or does it take a...
Yeah, that's why the גמרא like says בית דין. The גמרא imagines
that there's some authority that's sort of over... I mean, there's also
some implicit rule... you mean like who's standing there? Well, that's why
the second מחשבה machshava is sort of saying this. It's like you
don't need a person to designate. The way in which the כהנים
Kohanim on the ground, on the floor are going to choose to
use it. Okay.
On the basic level of rules, let's say, you know, on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, if one of the two pairs is lost, and
you... how would this idea of a general... it's already been sacrificed
for this...
Right, so, and
I mean, I think that's a good point, like are there certain
things like there where certain rituals are required where you don't have
the same degree of flexibility. So maybe it doesn't work for everything,
okay, but at least for generic קרבנות it would. All right, let's
just get to the next bit. ועוד זאת בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו שעיר
הנעשה בפנים. Ve'od zos betumas mikdash vekodashav sa'ir hana'aseh bifnim.
Now one last thing that the inner קרבן korban. is doing on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur if you remember, one of the things that
it was doing was when you were not aware at the beginning
that you were טמא, tamei, you did something wrong and now you're
not yet aware at the end. So the whole big deal of
the inner קרבן korban of יום כיפור Yom Kippur is just to
deal with that form of טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash? but the other
thing it deals with is willful טומאת מקדש. tumas mikdash Okay? מנלן
מילי, Menalan milei, how do you know that the inner קרבן of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur, deals with willful טומאת מקדש? tumas mikdash Because
דתנו רבנן, detanu rabanan, וכפר על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל ומפשעיהם לכל
חטאתם. vechiper al hakodesh mitumos benei Yisrael umipisheihem lechol chatosam. So the
חטאתם chatosam we דרשן darshan before meant something that could become a
חטאת, chatas, so something that you were aware of at the beginning
but not yet aware at the end. Now we're going to explain
the word פשעיהם, pisheihem, which is a willful sin. פשעים אלו המרדים,
Pesha'im elu hamardim, these are the rebellious sins, willful sins. וכן הוא
אומר מלך מואב פשע בי, vechein hu omer melech mo'av pasha bi,
you know, rebelled against me. ואומר אז תפשע לבנה בעת ההיא, ve'omer
az tifsha livnah ba'es hahi, then the, okay, בעת ההיא. ba'eta hi.
חטאות אלו השגגות, Chata'os elu hashgagous, the sins, those are the unintentional.
וכן הוא אומר נפש כי תחטא בשגגה. vechein hu omer nefesh ki
techeta bishgaga. So the same way the חטאות chata'os are the טומאת
מקדש tumas mikdash. that are done in a certain form of not
knowing, so the פשעים pesha'im are willful טומאת מקדש and both of
those are done by the inner קרבן. Okay, we'll just start the
next piece. Now we have finally, you paid your dues everybody, for
the first twelve דף or whatever it is, now we're finally going
to get to the part of the משנה Mishnah, that deals with
what the goat that's sent off the cliff and how it atones
for all the rest of your sins, because I know that most
people here are not worried too much about their sins of טומאת
מקדש. So, now we get to the rest of your sins. על
שאר עבירות שבתורה, Al shear aveiros shebatorah, all the rest, the heavy,
the light ones, willful, not willful, knowing and not knowing, עשה's, aseh
לא תעשה's, lo ta'aseh כרת, kares, חיוב בית דין, chiyuv beis din,
the goat that goes off the cliff atones. So the גמרא first
just wants to understand that some of this sounds redundant. היינו קלות
היינו עשה, Hainu kalos hainu aseh, you said the light ones and
then you said the positive ones. What's a light transgression other than
the non-fulfillment of a positive? I'm sorry, היינו עשה ולא תעשה hainu
aseh velo ta'aseh or just a simple לא תעשה lo ta'aseh as
opposed to one with a more weighty punishment. חמורות, Chamuros, you said
the weighty ones, היינו כריתות ומיתות בית דין. hainu krisous umisous beis
din. Those are כרת kares and מיתות בית דין. misous beis din.
So why did you list light, you said whether light or heavy,
whether עשה aseh or לא תעשה lo ta'aseh or כרת kares or
מיתות בית דין? misous beis din? That's exactly why they're heavy, the
גמרא explains. I understand. Okay. Now also, הודע היינו מזיד, Hoda hainu
meizid, if you're aware of it, that means that you're willful. לא
הודע, Lo hoda, you're not aware, היינו שוגג, hainu shogeg, it means
you're a שוגג. shogeg. So you already said מזיד meizid and שוגג.
shogeg. So what are these extra words doing? So אמר רב יהודה
הכי קאמר, amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar, this is what it's saying.
על שאר עבירות שבתורה, Al shear aveiros shebatorah, בין קלות בין חמורות,
bein kalos bein chamuros, whether heavy or light, whether light or heavy.
בין שעשאן בשוגג בין שעשאן במזיד. Bein she'asaan bishogeg bein she'asaan bimeizid.
Okay, so far that's what we've said. אותן שעשאן בשוגג, Otan she'asaan
bishogeg, now we're going to explain the terms הודע hoda and לא
הודע. lo hoda. Those that you did בשוגג, bishogeg, בין נודע לו
ספקן בין לא נודע לו ספקן. bein noda lo sfekan bein lo
noda lo sfekan. הודע Hoda could mean the classic meaning of the
word הודע hoda is I did something בשוגג, bishogeg, now I'm aware
of it. That's הודע. hoda. It doesn't mean I was aware when
I sinned. It means now I'm aware that I have sinned. But
we can't explain the word הודע hoda in the משנה to be
that. Because if I actually did something wrong like I ate חלב
chelev בשוגג bishogeg and now I'm aware that I sinned, what's my
obligation? To do what? To bring a חטאת. chatas. So יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur the הלכה halacha is, does not get me out of
a קרבן that I'm חייב chayav in. Okay, there I already have
a personal concrete way of atoning. יום כיפור Yom Kippur doesn't get
me out of a חטאת. chatas.
But does it suspend the punishment till you do?
Right. But if it says בין הודע, bein hoda, יום כיפור Yom
Kippur is not מכפר mechaper when I'm aware that I did a
שוגג. shogeg. Then I have to bring a חטאת. chatas. So הודע
hoda doesn't mean מזיד, meizid, הודע hoda means I'm aware now after
I sinned, but יום כיפור Yom Kippur doesn't get me out of
that. So the one case
that... An אשם. Asham. אשם תלוי. Asham talui. Okay, so let's say
now it's ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur and I'm aware that
I might have eaten חלב. chelev. Okay, there was two pieces of
meat in front of me, one was חלב, chelev, one wasn't. I
didn't realize it, somebody told me after. Now I'm aware I might
have eaten חלב. chelev. You know what I'm obligated to bring? An
אשם תלוי. Asham talui. That יום כיפור Yom Kippur gets me off
the hook for. After יום כיפור Yom Kippur passes, even if I
became aware that I might have sinned, I no longer have to
bring an אשם תלוי. Asham talui. If I become aware that I
definitely sinned, I'll bring a חטאת, chatas, okay? So that's how we're
explaining the הודע. hoda. You became aware of a sin, but not
of a sin you definitely did, then יום כיפור Yom Kippur wouldn't
help. Of a sin you might have done. Okay.
So let's just read that, where were we? בין נודע לא ספקן,
Bein noda lo sefekan, you're aware that you might have sinned and
you would be normally חייב chayav in אשם תלוי. asham talui. בין
נודע לא ספקן, Bein noda lo sefekon, or you're not aware that
you might have sinned, so יום כיפור Yom Kippur gets you out
of the אשם תלוי Asham talui stuff. The one thing it doesn't
get you out of is a definite חיוב chiyuv of a חטאת.
chatas. ואלו הן הקלות—now V'elu hen hakalot that's dealing with the הודע
לא הודע. hoda-lo-hoda. How about the redundancy of light and heavy? Alright,
it's redundant. We're just being more specific. ואלו הן הקלות—by V'elu hen
hakalot the way, if you want to know what are the light
ones—עשה ולא תעשה. Aseh v'lo taaseh. ואלו הן החמורות—here V'elu hen hachamurot
are the heavy ones—כריתות ומיתות בית דין. Kritot umitot beit din. Okay.
And that's where we was, so we will continue tomorrow, now that
we've parsed the משנה, we will continue tomorrow with the discussion of
what is the goat of יום כיפור מכפר mechaper for. See you
all tomorrow.